Oleg Shpynov

oleg.shpynov@gmail.com

Shuvalovsky pr. 84 135 Saint-Petersburg Russia 197345

April 7th, 1986 +7 904 331 35 04



Summary

Seasoned research engineering leader with strong math background, good communication and teamwork skills. I am leading a group that develops machine learning algorithms and scalable computational bioinformatics pipelines for biological data analysis. Previously I was focused on Integrated Development Environment development from lexical analysis to advanced type systems development and semantic verifications.

Experience

2013 - today

Research and Development Team Lead

JetBrains Research, Saint-Petersburg, Russia

Head of research and development bioinformatics group. Group is developing novel algorithms and methods for experimental data analysis, building scalable computational pipelines and tools, and working in collaboration with biologists on various ageing studies.

- Built a team of software developers with expertise in machine learning and bioinformatics
- Lead development of two bioinformatics products: JBR Genome Browser and SPAN Semi-supervised Peak Analyzer
- Developed various open source libraries including Viktor (fast f64 computations for Kotlin), Bioinf-commons (Bioinformatics library in Koltin), big (BigBed/Wig files format support for JVM), npy (Numpy arrays support for JVM)
- · Onboarding and mentoring software developers of all levels
- Coordinated research and development activities in collaborations with biologists
- Developed scientific papers search and analyze service PubTrends

Applied technologies: Unix, Java, Kotlin, Swing, Python, Jupyter, Pandas, Matplotlib, Docker, Docker Compose, PostgreSQL, Neo4j, Flask, Celery, Nltk, Pytorch, HTML, CSS, Javascript, React, Bootstrap, Git, GitHub, AWS, Continuous Integration TeamCity

Group website: https://research.jetbrains.org/groups/biolabs

GitHub account: https://github.com/olegs

2014 - today | **Students mentor**

Computer Science Center, Saint-Petersburg, Russia Higher School of Economics, Saint-Petersburg, Russia Bioinformatics Institute, Saint-Petersburg, Russia

Mentored various student project in software development and machine learning including two successful Masters dissertations

2017 - 2018 | Visiting Research Scientist

Department of Pathology and Immunology, Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis, MO, USA

Computational lead in a joint project of Maxim Artyomov Lab at Washington University in St.Louis . Worked on applied machine learning approaches and methods for epigenetic data analysis.

- Built scalable high-performance computational pipelines targeting Portable Batch System
- Analyzed data for various biological experimental
- · Created web resource portals for experimental data

Applied technologies: Unix, QSUB, Bash, Snakemake, Java, Kotlin, Python, Jupyter, Pandas, Matplotlib, Pytest, Git, Docker, Continuous Integration TeamCity, HTML, CSS, Javascript, Bootstrap, Word, Excel, Adobe Illustrator

Project website: https://artyomovlab.wustl.edu/aging

2006 - 2013 | Senior software developer

JetBrains, Saint-Petersburg, Russia

Main focus was on the analysis of source code in programming languages, starting from lexical analysis to advanced type system development and source code semantic verifications.

- Developed JetBrains products: flagship tool IntellIJ IDEA, PyCharm
- Created RubyMine Integrated Development Environment for Ruby programming language
- Maintained and developed IdeaVIM plugin (vim emulation plugin, 7+mln downloads)
- Took part in various IntelliJ IDEA plugins development: GitHub integration support, web-markup languages editing capabilities like YAML, SCSS, LESS, etc.
- Participated in a number of conferences on Ruby on Rails as a company representative and a speaker
- Author of various blog posts on Rubymine, IntelliJ IDEA, etc.

Applied technologies: Ruby, Rails, Unix, Java, Concurrency, IDE, Swing, Git, GitHub, Continuous Integration TeamCity

Website: https://www.jetbrains.com/

Education

of Washington University in St.Louis, Saint-Petersburg, Russia	2019	Deep learning nanodegree at Udacity, certificate number: 9GSNRHUA
of Washington University in St.Louis, Saint-Petersburg, Russia		Machine learning, deep learning, models deployment
of Washington University in St.Louis, Saint-Petersburg, Russia		
	2016	Systems Biology Workshop by Bioinformatics Institute, University ITMO and Artyomov Lab
System level data ranging from gone expression DNA ChID and example cognition unit		
		System level data ranging from gene expression, RNA-, ChIP-, and exome-sequencing up to
high-throughput metabolomics and network-based data integration.		high-throughput metabolomics and network-based data integration.
2045 M. C.M. I. I	2015	M. GM I. I III. GI IM. G.D
2015 Microsoft Machine Learning and Intelligence School, Microsoft, Russia	2015	
Machine learning, artificial intelligence, statistics.		Machine learning, artificial intelligence, statistics.
2011 - 2012 Saint-Petersburg Academic University — Nanotechnology Research and Education Centr	2011 - 2012	Saint-Petersburg Academic University — Nanotechnology Research and Education Centre
of the Russian Academy of Sciences, Russia	2011 2012	
Classes of bioinformatics, molecular biology, statistics.		
classes of Biomiermanes, moreoutar Biology, statustics.		oldsood of Bioliforniation, morocatal Biology, statutorics.
2008 - 2010 Post graduate student (PhD) in Computer Science, Faculty of Mathematics and Mechanic	2008 - 2010	Post graduate student (PhD) in Computer Science, Faculty of Mathematics and Mechanics,
Saint-Petersburg State University, Russia		
2003 - 2008 Masters in Computer Science, score 4.8 of 5. Saint-Petersburg State University, Russia	2003 - 2008	Masters in Computer Science, score 4.8 of 5. Saint-Petersburg State University, Russia
Faculty of Mathematics and Mechanics, Department of System Programming		Faculty of Mathematics and Mechanics, Department of System Programming

Publications

2020	I. Shchukina, J. Bagaitkar, O. Shpynov et al. "Epigenetic changes in aging human monocytes",
	Nature Aging, in review,
	preprint https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.05.10.087023v1
2019	O. Shpynov, A. Dievskii, P. Tsurinov, et al. "Bioinformatics Institute 2018/19 project
	abstracts", Saint-Petersburg, Russia
2015	S. Lebedev, R. Chernyatchik, O. Shpynov "CMeth: a Bayesian semiparametric model for
	differential methylation analysis",
	preprint https://research.jetbrains.org/files/material/5eb189e5911b1.pdf

Languages

Russian Native English Fluent

Honors and Awards

Graduated Saint-Petersburg State University cum laude Participated in ACM regional contests on programming as university team Winner of Saint-Petersburg state school contests on math, physics, programming

Interests

Machine learning, software development, Bioinformatics. Traveling, hiking, snowboarding, diving, cycling, photography.